Finding Aid for David R. Bassett Papers, 1963-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
David R. Bassett Papers 1963-2004, 1972-2000
Bassett, David R., 1928-
9 linear feet
9466 Aa 2
Physician and pacifist active in movement of conscientious objectors opposing use of their taxes for military purposes; chairperson and honorary national chairperson of the National Council for a World Peace Tax Fund (name changed in 1985 to National Campaign for a Peace Tax Fund). Pacifist Issues series includes materials collected and created by Bassett on a variety of pacifist issues, primarily war tax resistance and conscientious objection; the Peace Tax Fund series consists of chronological files and topological files relating to the work of the National Campaign for a Peace Tax Fund; and series of manuals, handbooks and reference materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 8242 ) was the gift of David R. Bassett in April 1994. A second gift was received in August 1994. A third gift was received in January 2005.
The collection is open to research.
Born September 7, 1928 in Taunton, Massachusetts, David R. Bassett has been active in pacifist movements, particularly conscientious objection to military taxation, for most of his life. After earning a bachelor's degree in social relations from Harvard College in 1949, Bassett pursued medical training at Tufts University, which he completed in 1953. A registered conscientious objector, Bassett participated in the Alternative Service program, providing health care in rural India from 1955 to 1957. Bassett's experiences in India fostered an interest in preventive medicine. Bassett returned to the United States to complete residency and fellowship training in Philadelphia, where he became a specialist in preventive cardiovascular disease. Bassett served as co-director and director of the Hawaii Cardiovascular Study at Queens Hospital in Honolulu, Hawaii, from 1963 to 1968, when he joined the Division of Hypertension at the University of Michigan Medical Center. Bassett retired from his position there as chief of the hyperlipidemia program in 1994.
Bassett, who was brought up in the Congregational Church, first began attending meetings of the Society of Friends while a student at Harvard. In 1950, after graduating, Bassett served with the American Friends Service Committee (AFSC) in Mexico. During his years in medical school, Bassett often worked with the AFSC weekend work camps in Boston, and later completed his alternative service in India under the auspices of the AFSC. In 1960, along with his wife, Miyoko Inouye, Bassett formally joined the strongly pacifist faith.
Bassett's convictions led him to become active in the anti-Vietnam War effort during his time in Hawaii. After moving to Ann Arbor, Bassett became increasingly involved in peace-related activities through the Ann Arbor Friends. The U.S. Peace Tax Fund Bill (originally the World Peace Tax Fund Bill), grew out of concern that registration with the government as a conscientious objector did not prevent Bassett's taxes from supporting an ever-growing defense budget. Bassett had already begun working for change on an individual level by deciding to withhold war taxes, but felt that the cause would be more effectively advanced through a legislative route. With the help of University of Michigan Law School Professor Joseph Sax and law student Michael Hall, Bassett drafted the peace tax fund bill. Another University of Michigan professor, Robert Lind of the School of Social Work, assisted by making contacts in the U.S. Congress, particularly members of the Black Caucus and other followers of Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Representative Ronald Dellums, of California agreed to sponsor the bill, which was first introduced on tax day April 15, 1972. The bill was not introduced in the Senate until 1977, when Senator Mark Hatfield of Oregon agreed to sponsor the initiative.
The National Council for a World Peace Tax Fund (NCWPTF), which began as a small group of supporters in the Ann Arbor area, became, by 1975, an organized campaign on a national level, with a full-time paid staff and offices in Washington D.C. Bassett, after serving for a year as the organization's first chairperson, was named honorary national chairperson in 1976. While other organizations protesting military taxation concentrated on tax resistance and other forms of civil disobedience, Bassett's group focused on a legislative solution to the problem. As stated in the Peace Tax Fund Bill that share of taxes which would ordinarily go to the defense budget could be diverted instead to a special fund if the taxpayer was a registered conscientious objector. Congress would use the fund to foster peace-related activities. In 1985, as part of changes made to the bill in an effort to improve its prospects, the name was changed to the U.S. Peace Tax Fund Bill, and the NCWPTF became the National Campaign for a Peace Tax Fund (NCPTF). Efforts to pass the legislation continue to the present time.
The David R. Bassett Papers document Bassett's activities in local and national peace-related organizations, most notably the peace tax fund movement from 1963 to 2002. The collection includes correspondence, minutes, agendas, memos, newspaper clippings, articles, interview transcripts, flyers, brochures, handouts, notes and newsletters, as well as a number of handbooks and manuals. The collection divides into four series. Pacifist Issues concern Bassett's peace-related activities. The next series, which makes up the bulk of the collection, contains the organizational records of the National Campaign for a Peace Tax Fund. The last two series are devoted to related groups, including Other Organizations based in the United States, or International groups devoted to peace tax funds or other peace-related causes.
Subjects:
Bassett, David R., 1928-; Conscientious objectors--Michigan.; National Campaign for a Peace Tax Fund.; National Council for a World Peace Tax Fund.; Pacifism.; War tax resistance--United States.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bassett, David R., 1928-; Dellums, Ronald V., 1935-; War tax resistance--United States.; International Conference on War Tax Resistance (8th: 2000: Washington, D.C.)
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Pacifist Issues 1960-2003
  The Pacifist Issues series comprises materials collected and created by Bassett on a variety of pacifist issues, but primarily materials on war tax resistance and conscientious objection. The topical files include correspondence, notes, articles and newspaper clippings. The topical files are followed by a sub-series concerning legal cases, including briefs from trials of war-tax resisters. The next sub-series documents articles written by Bassett, and talks he gave, mainly on the Peace Tax Fund, to various groups around Michigan and the vicinity. A small sub-series contains interviews by and of Bassett, including one cassette tape, two VHS videotapes. There are also several photographs of Bassett and Congressman Ronald Dellums. The articles sub-series includes a draft, along with comments by readers, of "Affirm Life: Pay for Peace," a major article on the Peace Tax Fund, which was later published in Handbook on Military Taxes & Conscience. A copy of the article can be found in the series, National Campaign for a Peace Tax Fund, as part of its publications sub-series in Box 6. The Pacifist Issues series also includes issues of The DePaul Law Review and Sojourners with substantial articles on the Peace Tax Fund issue
  - Topical Files
    - Amnesty for draft registers 1972-1974 (Box 1)
    - Conscientious objection
      - Conscientious Objection, Carl Cohen 1979, 1983, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Conscientious Objection, International 1978, 1981, 1983, 1989 (Box 1)
      - Conscientious Objection, Military 1974-1975, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
      - Conscientious Objection, Religious Traditions 1975-1984 (Box 1)
      - Conscientious Objector Act of 1992 (Box 1)
      - Conscientious Objection, War Tax Resistance 1971-1974, 1982-1986, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Economic Analyses 1971, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Kornhauser, Marjorie, Articles and Correspondence 1999-2000, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Militarism, Articles 1981 (Box 1)
    - Report by the Comptroller-General of the U.S.: Illegal Tax Protesters Threaten Tax System GGD81-83 July 8, 1981 (Box 1)
    - War Tax Resistance 1971-1991 (Box 1)
    - War Tax Resistance, Publications 1976-1979, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Legal Cases
    - General 1971-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Adams, Priscilla 1997-2003, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Browne, Gordon and Edith 1982 (Box 1)
    - Cumbee, Jack and Judith undated (Box 1)
    - Packard, Rosa 1997-2003, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Philadelphia Yearly Meeting (Friends) 2003 (Box 1)
  - Articles
    - Bassett, David R., Profiles 1994-1995, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - International Movements, Articles and Speeches 1987 (Box 1)
    - Peace Tax Fund, Articles 1987 (Box 1)
    - "War Tax Concerns" (chapter 6 of Handbook of Military Taxes and Conscience, by Linda Coffin), 1985 (Box 1)
    - "War Tax Concerns," Reactions to First Draft 1986 (Box 1)
    - "War Tax Concerns," Bibliography 1987 (Box 1)
  - Interviews
    - Amidei, Nancy (interview conducted by David R. Bassett) 1985 (Box 2)
    - Sax, Joseph (interview conducted by David R. Bassett) 1984 (Box 2)
    - World Peace Tax Fund: A History (interview with David R. Bassett) (Box 2)
  - Multimedia
    - Eighth International Conference on War Tax Resistance 2000
      - Highlights of Conference, VHS videotape (Box 2)
      - Friday Afternoon April 7, 2000, VHS videotape (Box 2)
    - "Harvey O. on the Metro: Interview with David Bassett," 4/17/1994, audio-cassette tape (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - David R. Bassett and Representative Ronald Dellums 1974 (Box 2)
  - Talks by David R. Bassett
    - Ann Arbor Friends Meeting forum, "Conscience and Military Taxes" 3/17/1993 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Friends Meeting; Update on World Peace Tax Fund March 1983 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor War Tax Dissidents 1/15/1987, 1/22/1987, 1/29/1987 (Box 2)
    - Berrian County Medical Society 3/19/1987 (Box 2)
    - Cable TV 10/30/1984 (Box 2)
    - Conscience and War Taxes, Ann Arbor Public Library 2/21/1985 (Box 2)
    - Hillsdale, MI 5/3/1983 (Hillsdale College) (Box 2)
    - Minicourses in "Free University" at U-M; Prepared by David R. Bassett 1983 (Box 2)
    - NCPTF address April 1984 (Box 2)
    - Physicians for Social Responsibility article and talk, Henry Ford Community College 12/18/1985 (Box 2)
    - War taxes and the Peace Tax Fund Bill (Box 2)
    - WUOM 2/17/1987 (Box 2)
- National Campaign for a Peace Tax Fund
  National Campaign for a Peace Tax Fund, the largest series of the collection, includes chronological and topical files, and NCPTF publications.
  - Chronological Files 1963-2003
    The chronological files comprise both NCPTF organizational records, and Bassett's personal notes and correspondence as honorary national chairperson. The chronological files contain correspondence, memos, notes, and agendas and minutes from meetings of NCPTF committees. These meetings include the steering committee from 1971 through 1984 (when the campaign was based in Ann Arbor), and the Board of Directors from 1985 to 2003. The 1985 folders document a series of major changes made in the bill, and its name change from World Peace Tax Fund Act to U.S. Peace Tax Fund Act. The folder titled "Legislation for Peace Tax Fund, 1971-1977" contains a rich collection of material documenting early efforts to acquire sponsorship for the fund in the U.S. House of Representatives. There is also a folder titled "Legislation preceding NCPTF (materials received from others), 1963-1969," which has materials from earlier war-tax resistance efforts.
    - Legislation Preceding NCPTF (materials received from others) 1963-1969 (Box 2)
    - Early Drafts and Information Regarding World Peace Tax Fund 1971 (Box 2)
    - Legislation for Peace Tax Fund 1971-1977 (Box 2)
    - Steering Committee Meetings 1971-1982, 11 folders (Box 2)
    - Working Committee 1972 (Box 2)
    - Michiana Regional Meetings 1975-1976, 1981-1983, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - National Council 1976 (Box 2)
    - Seminar/Visitation 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Steering Committee Meetings 1983-1984, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Task Force on Taxes 1983 (Box 3)
    - Changes to World Peace Tax Fund Bill 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - Annual Meetings 1984-1987, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Board Meetings 1985-1992, 13 folders (Box 3)
    - Congressional Hearings 1991-1992, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Congressional Hearings, Press Packet 1992 (Box 3)
    - Annual Meetings 1993, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Board Meetings 1993, 1998-2003, 20 folders (Box 4)
  - Topical Files
    The topical files cover a variety of issues, such as the reaction of the Internal Revenue Service to the peace tax fund proposals, the campaign's fundraising efforts, and early drafts of the Peace Tax Fund Bill. There are notable folders concerning NCPTF bylaws and policies, and the experiences of individual war tax resisters (such as the parent/son letters of Bob Blood). The folder "Peace Tax Fund Bill, Congressional records, 1975-1991" contains copies of the official versions of the bill as well as excerpts from debate on the bill in the House and the Senate.
    - Abortion and the Peace Tax Fund 1989 (Box 4)
    - Archives at Swarthmore College 1989 (Box 4)
    - Articles of Incorporation and By-Laws 1984-1985, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Boardman, Elizabeth 1972 (Box 4)
    - Celebration of Conscience, Bryn Mawr 1990 (Box 4)
    - Clearness Committee 1998 (Box 4)
    - Congressional District Contacts
      - Manual 1990 (Box 4)
      - Packet 1984 (Box 4)
      - Tax Day Motivational Packet 1996, 1999 (Box 4)
      - Program 2001-2002 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence with Congressmen 1983, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Eliot, Frances 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    - Finances 2002 (Box 4)
    - Freeman, Harrop (withdrawal of sponsorship) 1983 (Box 5)
    - Fund for Conscience 1989 (Box 5)
    - Fundraising
      - 1984-1985 (Box 5)
      - 1992 (Box 5)
      - (Letter never sent) 1993 (Box 5)
      - Membership Database 1998 (Box 5)
      - Major Donors 2001 (Box 5)
      - Major Donors, George Wald 1992 (Box 5)
      - Major Donors, Stephen Serafin 2000-2002 (Box 5)
      - Packet 1992 (Box 5)
    - Hawaii Committee 1973 (Box 5)
    - Internal Revenue Service
      - Bassett, David and Miyoko 1980-1981 (Box 5)
      - Blood, Bob 1966-1968 (Box 5)
      - Reagle, Greg, correspondence 2002 (Box 5)
    - Legal Issues 1972-1990 (Box 5)
    - "Legislative Basis of the Peace Tax" (manuscript) 1985-1987 (Box 5)
    - Lobbying
      - Michigan 1975-1979 (Box 5)
      - Michigan 1982-1990 (Box 5)
      - Washington, D.C. 1982-1983 (Box 5)
      - Washington, D.C. 1992 (Box 5)
      - Washington, D.C. 2001 (Box 5)
    - Local Supporters 1980, 1982, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Membership lists 1975-1989 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - National Council Proposal 1980-1983 (Box 5)
    - New York Times 2002 (Box 5)
    - Peace Tax Foundation Video 1992 (Box 5)
    - Peace Tax Fund Bill
      - Congressional Records 1975-1991 (Box 5)
      - Drafts and Revisions 1971-1992 (Box 5)
      - Lobbying Congress 1982-1985 (Box 5)
      - Petitions 1998-1999 (Box 5)
      - Responses 1970-1975, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Responses 1993, 1995, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Pursell, Carl (U.S. Congress), correspondence 1978-1986 (Box 5)
    - School Curriculum, Peace-making 1979 (Box 5)
    - Slide show for NCPTF 1986 (Box 5)
    - Staff
      - Barouch, Rita 1974 (Box 5)
      - Brown, Chris 1974-1976 (Box 5)
      - Fulton, Leah (initial contact person) 1972-1974 (Box 5)
      - Garren, Bruce 1972-1973 (Box 5)
      - Lauder, Ruth 1974-1975 (Box 5)
      - McNeil, Gelson 1973-1974 (Box 5)
      - Samuel, Bill 1975 (Box 5)
      - Stellard, Ralph (application) 1982 (Box 5)
    - Statement on September 11, 2001 (Box 6)
    - Supporters 1972-1975 (Box 6)
    - Survey on Conscientious Objection 1988 (Box 6)
    - "Visionaries," Documentary Proposal 1998 (Box 6)
    - War tax resistance counselor's packet, prepared by Frances Eliot and David R. Bassett 1984 (Box 6)
  - Publications
    The series concludes with a small collection of publications put out by the NCPTF. Although not a complete run, the Newsletters are particularly useful for their summary of the progress of the campaign. Also included in this sub-series are a number of brochures and handouts created by the NCPTF for informational and publicity purposes.
    - Activist Guide: Speaking for Conscience 1997 (Box 6)
    - Affirm Life, Pay for Peace: A Handbook for World Peace Tax Fund Educators and Organizers 1981 (Box 6)
    - Manual for Peace Tax Fund Action 1985 (Box 6)
    - Motivational Packet 1983 (Box 6)
    - NCPTF Newsletter (incomplete) 1984-2004, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Pamphlets 1975, 1979-1980, 1990-1992 (Box 6)
    - Pre-Income-Tax-Day Campaign Kit, Dayton Conference 1974 (Box 6)
    - War Tax Resistance Counseling Packets 1984-1985, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Other Organizations 1967-2004
  - General 1985-1987, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, Ann Arbor 1983-1986 (Box 6)
  - Ann Arbor Friends Meeting 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Ann Arbor Friends Meeting, New Call to Peacemaking 1978, 1980-1984, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Ann Arbor Friends, Peace and Social Concerns Survey 1993 (Box 6)
  - Ann Arbor Life Priorities Fund 1972 (Box 6)
    (from Frances Eliot)
  - Ann Arbor War Tax Dissidents, War Tax Resistance Counseling Packet 1982-1983 (Box 6)
  - Ann Arbor Vigils, Federal Building 1986 (Box 6)
  - Ann Arbor War Tax Resistance 1978 (Box 6)
  - Archdiocese of Detroit, Office for Justice and Peace, Gospels and Christian Peace-making Packet 1978 (Box 6)
  - Center on Law and Pacifism, "People Pay for Peace," 1982 (Box 6)
  - Coalition for Peace in Central America, Vigil 1986 (Box 6)
  - Conscience and Military Tax Campaign
    - 1982-1986, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Newsletters 1985, 1987-1994 (Box 6)
    - "Peace Tax Fund," 1986 (Box 6)
    - Pearson, Edward 1979, 1982, 1987-1993 (Box 6)
  - Friends Committee on National Legislation, Lake Erie Yearly Meeting 1983 (Box 7)
  - Friends Committee on National Legislation, Washington, D.C. 1995-1999 (Box 7)
  - Friends Committee on War Tax Concerns
    - "Fear God and Honor the Emperor," 1988 (Box 7)
    - Handbook on Military Taxes and Conscience 1988 (Box 7)
    - War Tax Legislation Essay 1985-1987 (Box 7)
  - "Friends Journal," Articles and Debate 1999-2000 (Box 7)
  - Friends Meeting of Washington 2003 (Box 7)
  - Friends Philadelphia Yearly Meeting 1980, 1985, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Friends Service Committee
    - Board Meeting 1998 (Box 7)
    - Conscientious Objection to Military Taxes 1997-1998 (Box 7)
    - Mike Yarrow (Board of Trustees) Statement About International Conciliation undated (Box 7)
  - Friends World Committee for Consultation, Gwatt Switzerland 1979 (Box 7)
  - Historic Peace Church Task Force on War Taxes 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - National War Tax Resistance Coordinating Committee
    - General 1984, 1990-1998, 2003 (Box 7)
    - Annual Meeting 1991 (Box 7)
    - Newsletters 1985-2004, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - War Tax Alternative Fund Resource Packet 1983 (Box 7)
  - Northern California War Tax Resistance, War Tax Resistance Counseling Packet circa 1983 (Box 7)
  - Peacemaker Movement, Handbook on Nonpayment of War Taxes 1967, 1977, 1981 (Box 7)
  - Peace Tax Foundation November 1986-April 1993 (Box 7)
  - Religious Society of Friends, Committee of Correspondence on War, Tax Concerns, and Support 1998-1999 (Box 7)
  - Religious Witness Against the Violence in South America 1986 (Box 7)
  - War Resisters' International
    - General 1990, 1995, 2001 (Box 7)
    - Conscientious Objector's Guide to the United Nations Human Rights System 2000 (Box 7)
    - Refusing to Bear Arms 1998, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - War Resisters' League, General 1990, 1997-2002 (Box 7)
- International Organizations and Activities 1974-2002
  - General 1979, 1983-1985 (Box 8)
  - Brett, Rachel. Quaker United Nations Office (Geneva, Switzerland) 2000-2001 (Box 8)
  - Conscience and Peace Tax International (Brussels, Belgium)
    - General 2000, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Mission and Project Proposals 2000 (Box 8)
    - Notes [Taken by David R. Bassett] 2000-2001 (Box 8)
    - Statement to the United Nations Commission on Human Rights 2000-2001 (Box 8)
  - Conscience Canada, Newsletters and Correspondence 1998-2000 (Box 8)
  - Conscience Canada, Jerrilyn Prior 1991 (Box 8)
  - European Network for Peace and Human Rights 2001-2002 (Box 8)
  - International Conference of Military Tax Resisters (Tubingen, Germany) 1986
    - General (Box 8)
    - Ann Arbor City Council (Box 8)
    - Hartmut Hanauske-Abel (Box 8)
    - Physicians (Box 8)
    - Post-Conference Correspondence (Box 8)
    - Printed Material (Box 8)
  - International Conference on War Tax Resistance (Vierhouten, Netherlands) 1988
    - General, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Printed Material (Box 8)
  - International Conference on War Tax Resistance (Aosta, Italy) 1990
    - General (Box 8)
    - Post-Conference Correspondence 1990-1991 (Box 8)
  - International Conference on War Tax Resistance (Brussels, Belgium) 1992
    - General (Box 8)
    - Background Notes (Box 8)
    - Non-Governmental Organization Status (Box 8)
    - Notes from the Conference [by David R. Bassett] (Box 8)
    - Personal Reactions [of David R. Bassett] (Box 8)
    - Post-Conference Correspondence (Box 8)
    - Preparatory Documents and Proceedings (Box 8)
    - Printed Material (Box 8)
    - Report on the Conference 1992-1993 (Box 8)
  - International Conference on War Tax Resistance (Hondarribia, Spain) 1994
    - General (Box 9)
    - Correspondence and notes (Box 9)
    - Declaration of Right of Non-Cooperation (Box 9)
    - Preparatory Documents and Proceedings (Box 9)
  - International Conference on War Tax Resistance (Hoddesdon, United Kingdom) 1996
    - General 1995-1997 (Box 9)
    - Background Notes (Box 9)
    - Letter to Family (Box 9)
    - Location for Next Conference (Box 9)
    - Proceedings (Box 9)
  - International Conference on War Tax Resistance (New Delhi, India) 1998-1999
    - General (Box 9)
  - International Conference on War Tax Resistance (Washington, D.C.) 2000
    - Bibliography (Box 9)
    - Budget 1999-2000 (Box 9)
    - Conference Packet (Box 9)
    - Final Report (Box 9)
    - Final Report, Distribution (Box 9)
    - Financial Assistance for Attendees (Box 9)
    - International Attendees and Visa Difficulties (Box 9)
    - Lawson, James (Civil Rights activist) (Box 9)
    - Photography (Box 9)
    - Post-Conference Tasks 1999-2000, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Pre-and Post-Conference Activity (Box 9)
    - Press Releases (Box 9)
    - Problematic Attendees (Box 9)
    - Protest of Internal Revenue Service (Washington, D.C.) (Box 9)
    - Reactions to the Conference (Box 9)
    - Registration (Box 9)
    - Thank-You Letters (Box 9)
    - Workshop on Conscience (Box 9)
    - Workshop on War Tax (Box 9)
  - Japanese Organizations 1974-1975 (Box 9)
  - Millennium Forum, Statement to the United Nations Millennium Summit 2000 (Box 9)
  - Place Research Center (Madrid, Spain) 1994 (Box 9)
  - Quaker Council for European Affairs (Brussels, Belgium) 2000 (Box 9)
  - Second Consultation on Peace and Human Rights. European Parliament (Brussels, Belgium) 2000 (Box 9)